My king.
お呼びですか
General.
どうなった？
We’ve starved them out,
作戦は成功しましたが
エホヤキンは言うことを聞きません
but Jehoiachin still refuses to meet.
Negotiations don’t concern me, General,
交渉しろなんて言ってない
but your incompetence does.
攻め落とすんだ！
もしできないなら
おまえの首が落ちることになるぞ！
Finish it,
or you’ll not find me as forgiving as the gods.
Yes, my king.
分かりました
大軍を率いるエホバはこう言っています
This is what Jehovah of armies says,
‘Because you did not obey my words,
あなたたちが私の言葉に従って
いないので この土地は荒廃する
‘all this land will be reduced to ruins,
‘and this land and its inhabitants
あなたたちは70年の間
バビロンの王に仕えなければならない
‘will have to serve the king of Babylon
for 70 years.’
Daniel!
ダニエル どこに行ってたの？
遅かったわね
Where have you been?
It’s almost sundown!
ごめんなさい エレミヤの話を聞いて
心配になって 神殿に行ってたんだ
Sorry, Jeremiah was speaking today, and I, uh
—I stopped by the temple on the way home.
もうすぐ晩ご飯よ
Well, we’re almost ready.
You were at the temple again today.
今日も神殿に行ってたんだな
I was.
うん
こんな気持ちかな
「エホバの麗しさを見つめ ・・・
“To gaze upon the pleasantness of Jehovah
and to look with appreciation upon his temple.”
神の神殿を感嘆して眺める」
I have something for you
これをおまえにあげよう
so you can always have Jehovah’s words with you.
エホバの言葉を忘れちゃいけないよ
Thank you, Papa.
ありがとう お父さん
What’s wrong?
どうした？
僕たちどうなるんだろう？
What’s going to happen to us?
What always happens to Jehovah’s faithful servants.
エホバは ご自分に仕える
人々を見捨てない
Have no fear, Jehovah is our shield.
怖がらなくていい
エホバが守ってくださる
Dinner’s ready.
ご飯できたわよ
Did you see our old neighbor at all?
お隣のおじいちゃんに会った？
No, I didn’t see him at all today.
今日は会ってないわ
Speaking of strange,
おかしいのよエリったら
この間もね・・・
I saw our neighbor Eli the other day.
Eli is always getting into trouble.
エリらしいね
じゃあ歌おうか
Let’s sing.
Son, pick a psalm.
ダニエル 何がいい？
「エホバは私の光 私の救い」
“Jehovah is my light and my salvation.”
You always choose that one.
またその歌？
Hushim.
フシム
「エホバ救う・・・
“Jehovah is my light
強い手で
“and my salvation.
Whom should I fear?”
恐れない」
お兄ちゃん
Daniel!
Stay and play?
どこ行くの？
お父さんと出掛けるんだ
I’ve got to go with Papa.
帰ってきたらノアの箱船ごっこしよう
When you come back, do you want to play Noah’s ark?
Sure.
いいよ リツパは何になる？
And who will you be?
I’ll be a lion.
私はライオン
Hmm.
うーん
じゃあお兄ちゃんはゾウ
Then I’ll be an elephant.
Jehoiachin has surrendered!
エホヤキンが降伏したらしい！
王が負けたんだ！
Jehoiachin has surrendered!
ユダ族のエベル 開けろ！
Household of Eber, tribe of Judah,
open up at once!
みんな表に出ろ！
All of you outside! Now!
大変だ！準備して！
It’s happened. They’re here.
Gather your things.
2人とも 荷物を持って 行くよ
We have to go.
Go?
パパ！どこに行くの？
Go where?
We don’t live here anymore.
もうここにはいられないんだ
Hushim, grab our bags.
フシム 荷物を持って！
I hate this place!
おうちに帰りたい
Let’s go inside.
おいで
開けろ！
Open up!
外に出ろ！奥を見てこい
All four—outside!
Check the back room.
By the order of the king, you are coming with us.
王の命令だ 一緒に来るんだ
ユダ族の ダニエルだな
Daniel, of the tribe of Judah—
おまえは 偉大な王
ネブカドネザルの王宮で訓練を受ける
You will receive training
in the house of the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
But this is my family.
僕の家はここです
Princes and nobles belong in the palace.
王族や貴族は
宮殿に住むことになったんだ
He’s not a prince; he’s just a boy.
何かの間違いではありませんか
ダニエル！
Daniel!
待ってください
私が代わりに行きます
Please, I will go if it’s a servant you seek.
駄目だ！
No! I’m taking the boy.
ダニエル！
Daniel!
Wait!
あの せめて別れを言わせてください
Can we say goodbye?
Make it quick.
さっさと済ませろ
勇気を出すんだ
Be strong, my son.
Jehovah is with you.
エホバが共にいてくださる
Daniel!
ダニエル！
Mishael.
ミシャエル ほかにもいるの？
Have you seen anyone else?
僕たちはいつも一緒だろ！
You didn’t think we’d let you come here alone, did you?
アザリヤ！
Azariah!
ハナニヤ！
Hananiah!
キスロンとアヒトブだよ
This is Chislon and Ahitub.
よろしく
Nice to meet you.
止まるんじゃない
Move along.
So where are we going?
どこに連れていかれるんだろう？
The palace, I guess.
宮殿じゃない？
ヨセフみたいに王宮かな？
So like Joseph in Pharaoh’s house?
No, like Joseph in the dungeon.
ヨセフみたいに地下牢かも
Doesn’t seem so bad to me.
結構いいとこじゃない？
Wait!
Chislon, look!
キスロン ほら声掛けろよ！
If you don’t say something, I will.
どうも
Hello.
これ あげる
Hi.
止まるな！
Move!
またね
Come back again sometime.
These are the Jewish boys that Ashpenaz summoned.
アシュペナズが集めた
ユダの若者たちです
You have been chosen
君たちが選ばれたのは優秀だからだ
because you are wise,
but you are lacking.
しかし
You will learn our writing
この国の言語と文学を学ぶ必要がある
and our language.
You will be given new names,
これから君たちの名前も変わる
and at the end of three years,
3年後 君たちは偉大な王
ネブカドネザルの家臣になる
you will serve the great King Nebuchadnezzar.
Today,
今 君たちは外国人だ
you are foreigners
だが 頑張れば
—tomorrow, the gods willing,
バビロニア人になれるんだ
Babylonians.
Meshach.
メシャク
You look like a Meshach.
バビロンらしい名前だね
Our new names sound like their gods.
バビロンの神みたい
New names, new language—
名前に言語
Soon they’ll want us to worship their gods.
次は宗教かな？
Calm down.
それがどうした？うちの親だって
エホバも偶像も崇拝してたぞ
My father had idols, and he worshipped Jehovah.
Did you see the same city I did?
ここはすごい所だ 世界の中心だ
It’s the center of the world.
We’ll even eat from the king’s table.
それに王と同じものを食べれる
What do Babylonians eat?
何食べてんだろ？
His servants are given only the best.
全て最高級品だ
これは食べちゃ駄目だ
We can’t eat from this food.
Why are you making a big deal out of this?
何言ってんだ
だって 汚れてるし
Because it’s unclean.
何か問題でもあるのか？
Is there a problem?
Our, uh, our God
あの 私たちの神が食べては
いけないと言ってるんです
doesn’t allow us to eat such foods.
神を畏れているのか？
You fear your God?
I do.
そうです
Well, I am afraid of my lord the king,
そうか
私は王を畏れている
who has assigned your food and drink.
王がおまえたちの
食べ物と飲み物を決めた
He insists on these selections
これは王直々の命令だ
to maintain your strength and vitality.
強く 健康になれと
ほかの若者と比べておまえたちの
顔色が悪かったらどうなる？
What if he should see you
looking worse in appearance
than the other youths?
You would make me guilty before the king.
私の首が飛ぶ
I must obey the king.
私は王に従わなければならない
So must you
おまえもだ
—all of you!
分かったな！
When dinner is served, I expect you to be hungry.
夕食は しっかり食べてもらおう
勝手に決めるなよ！
You don’t speak for us!
You’re right.
そうだね それぞれが決めることだよね
You can make your own choice.
そうじゃない！
僕たちに決める権利なんかない
Didn’t you hear him?
We don’t have a choice.
This is a new land with new laws.
国も法律も違うんだ
So what if some of the food is unbled?
血を気にしているのか？
It’s just food!
関係ないだろ！
エホバは血を食べてはならないと命じた
But Jehovah commanded us not to eat blood.
解釈の問題だろ！
That’s your interpretation.
“You must not eat . . . any blood at all.”
「血は一切食べてはならない」
What’s to interpret in that?
はっきりしてる
Maybe we should all take a moment and pray.
こういうときこそ みんなで祈ろう
Pray.
祈る？ここでか？
Here.
意味ないだろ
What’s the point?
エホバはイスラエルにいる
ここはバビロンだ
Jehovah is in Israel.
We’re in Babylon now.
どこにいてもエホバは
祈りを聞いてくださる
Don’t you believe that Jehovah is here too?
Jehovah said that we’re his witnesses.
僕たちはエホバの証人なんだ
What will people say about Jehovah
妥協して律法を破ったら
エホバの評判はどうなる？
if we give in and break his laws?
食事の時間です
Your meal is ready.
Did you hear me?
聞いてた？
はい
Thank you.
But if we eat those foods, we’ll disobey our God.
でも 食べると神に背くことになります
何も食べないのか？
Do you want to starve?
No, of course not,
違います
but He forbids us from eating blood
血と汚れたものは
食べることを許されていません
and food that he calls “unclean.”
Please, test your servants for ten days,
どうか 私たちを
10日の間試してください
and let us be given some vegetables to eat
幾らかの野菜と 水があれば十分です
and water to drink.
Vegetables?
野菜か？
Just give us ten days.
お願いです 10日でいいんです
And then deal with your servants
その上で 私たちをどうすべきか
ご判断ください
according to what you see.
Ten days.
10日の間
Here you go, thanks to Jehovah.
エホバに感謝しよう
You need to try this meat. It’s amazing!
この肉食べてみなよ！
Have you seen anything like this before?
こんなの初めてだよ！
Oh! Really!
Yes! Oh, wow!
ああ！
Yes!
よし！
アシュペナズがお呼びです
Ashpenaz has summoned you.
お連れしました こちらはユダの・・・
My lord, these young men are of royal . . .
分かっている！
I know who they are.
We’ve been watching you
おまえたちのことは見ていた
—all of you.
ずっとだ
バビロンの神々にひざまずかない
You don’t bow to our idols,
you pray only to your God,
自分の神にしか祈らない
準備したごちそうも食べない
and you are not eating our foods.
神が禁じている
と言うもので 少し・・・
They insisted that their God would not . . .
でも
Somehow,
you look healthier than the others.
みんな元気そうだ
これからも 希望する
食べ物を出してあげなさい
Continue giving them the diet they’ve requested.
And Belteshazzar,
ベルテシャザル
your future is bright.
君は前途有望だ
チャンスを無駄にするなよ
Don’t waste it.
Bring in the next group.
次！
The total rations would be fifteen kurru,
配給量は合計15クル
two p{
2パヌ 5スツです
and five s{
Correct.
よし
How much interest
お金や穀物に掛けることができる
利息は幾らか？
may a merchant charge on money and grain?
It would be 40 percent, my lord.
40％かと思います
Forty percent?
40？
Have you learned only to be a thief
3年間泥棒の勉強をしてきたのか？
the past three years?
どうだメシャク
And you, Meshach?
The rate is 20 percent.
利息は20％です
いいだろう
Very good.
エンリルのどの星が
ウルグラ座の中で一番明るいか？
Which star of Enlil is brightest
in the Urgula constellation?
Do you know?
どうだ？
It is the Lugal star.
それはルガルです
Impressive.
大したもんだ
There is a tower that is high
高い塔なのに影がない
but, nonetheless, has no shade.
何のことか？
What is it?
ジッグラトでしょうか
Your ziggurat?
話にならん
Hopeless.
You can solve the riddle?
分かるのか？
It is sunlight, my lord.
太陽の光です
Correct.
よし
My wise men teach that the gods
この国の賢人たちは 何事も
神々の定めだと教えている
are responsible for everything.
であるなら 善人が苦しみ
悪人が栄えるのはなぜか
If that’s so,
why do the good suffer and the evil prosper?
それは難し過ぎるのでは・・・
No one has been able to answer . . .
こうあります 王よ
As you say, O king,
「賢い人がいつも食事に
ありつけるとは限らない
‘the wise do not always have the food,
‘nor do the intelligent always have the riches,
知的な人が裕福になるとも
‘nor do those with knowledge always have success,
知識がある人が成功するとも限らない
‘because time and unexpected events
思いも寄らないことが
いつ誰にでも起きるからだ」
overtake them all.’
誰の言葉だ？
Who wrote those words?
Solomon.
ソロモンです
ソロモンの知恵か
Famed for his wisdom.
でもその知恵を与えたのは
But its source was his God,
ソロモンの神 私たちの神エホバです
our God, Jehovah.
Take them away.
下がれ
次はいつですか
When should we return?
次はない
You won’t!
もうおまえたちに用はない
Go back to your families.
使い物にならん
You’ve proven worthless.
ベルテシャザル おまえたち4人は残れ
Belteshazzar, no—not the four of you.
話がある
We have more to discuss.
おまえたちの神のことはよく知らないが
I do not know your God,
but you’ve proven to be ten times better
おまえたちは国中の
どの魔術師よりも10倍優れている
than any priest or conjurer that I’ve met.
Ashpenaz will arrange
アシュペナズの下
宮殿で賢人たちと働いてもらう
for you to serve in the palace with my wise men.
エルサレムでおまえたちの
才能は埋もれていた
Maybe your gifts were wasted in Jerusalem,
ここでなら十分に生かせるだろう
but here they will be put to use.
The victory in Jerusalem is complete.
エルサレムはついに陥落しました
続いてティルスの攻略を進めます
Our forces are now preparing to besiege Tyre.
ゼデキヤも大したことなかったな
They should remember what happened to Zedekiah.
神々を味方に付けたな！
The gods are with us!
Jerah,
エラハ どうした？
what is it?
エルサレムからです
It’s about Jerusalem.
Where are you going?
どちらへ？
家族に会ってくる
To see my family.
今年は大変だったわね
This year, we’ve had to make do.
Daniel.
ダニエル？
Come, eat.
座りなさい 食べて！
What’s wrong?
どうしたの？
It’s Jerusalem.
エルサレムが ・・・
They tore down the walls;
城壁が崩され 塔が焼かれた
they torched its towers.
Many died.
大勢が死に ・・・
And they burned down Jehovah’s house!
エホバの家が焼け落ちた！
Why didn’t our people listen?
警告されていたのに！
エホバは見ていない
とでも思っていたのか？
Did they think Jehovah couldn’t see
what they were doing?
As long as our temple existed,
神殿さえ残っていれば
our people had hope.
まだ望みがあったのに！
As long as Jehovah exists,
エホバは生きておられる
we have hope.
望みはあるわ
エホバは私たちを見捨てた
But he’s rejected us
because of our unrighteousness.
私たちが悪を行ったからだ
He hasn’t
いや みんなではないよ
—not everyone.
エホバはエゼキエルに
こう言ったそうだよ
Jehovah told Ezekiel
that in his eyes you
おまえダニエルが
あのノアやヨブのように
are as righteous as Noah
正しい人だと
and Job.
He said that?
本当に？
He did.
そうだよ
エホバがそこまで思ってくれているなら
If Jehovah cares so much,
どうしてまだバビロンにいるの？
then why are we in exile?
なぜエルサレムに帰れないの？
Why can’t we go home?
どうして家族で一緒に住めないの？
Why can’t we be together?
You are home, Son.
今一緒にいるじゃないか
I don’t have all the answers.
父さんにも分からないことがある
でもエホバから離れてはいけないよ
Stay close to Jehovah.
エホバは共にいてくださる
You will be blessed.
Call the wise men!
賢人たちを呼べ！
夢を見たんだ
I had a dream,
気になって仕方がない
だが思い出せない
and I’m agitated.
I need to know what I dreamed.
王が生き続けますように
どのような夢かお話しください
O king, may you live on forever.
Relate the dream to your servants.
We will tell the interpretation.
そうすれば解き明かします
No!
なんだと！もしおまえたちが夢の
内容を話さず 解き明かさないなら
If you don’t make the dream known to me
along with the interpretation,
you’ll be dismembered,
and your houses will be turned into public latrines.
手足を切り取って
おまえたちの家を公衆便所にしてやる
But if you do, tell me the dream
だが もし夢の内容を話し
解き明かすなら
and the interpretation,
you will receive gifts and a reward
褒美を与えよう
大きな栄誉も与えてやる！
and great honor.
We’ve got to buy some time
so we can consult the spirits.
伺いを立てるには時間が必要だ
The scrolls will tell you what the dreams say.
巻物に何か載っていないか？
We need to come up with a plan.
何か手を打たないと
He wants us to tell him the dream!
どんな夢だったかを話せだって！
Yes.
そうだ
No one has ever asked this before.
むちゃくちゃだ！どうしたらいいんだ！
Can we do it?
What do we do?
If you can buy us some time,
we can consult the spirits.
とにかく時間が要る
何とかしてみる
時間を稼いでいるのか？早くしろ！
You’ve agreed to tell me something false
and deceitful until the situation changes.
おまえたちはいつも
うそばかり言ってきた！
お言葉ですが・・・
Deceitful?
逆らうつもりか？
Deceitful!
There is not a man on earth
無理です そんなこと誰にもできません
who can do what the king demands.
What the king is asking is difficult.
難し過ぎます 王に説明
できるのは 神々だけでしょう
No one exists who could tell this to the king except
—except the gods.
Arioch,
アルヨク 捕らえろ！
seize them!
待て！
Down!
処刑しろ！
Kill them!
Call the wise men!
賢人たちを集めろ！急げ！
Hurry!
Go, go, go!
早くしろ！王の命令だ 連れてこい！
By the order of the king, round them up!
エラハ
Jerah.
You’re in danger.
逃げてください
何かあったのか？
Why? What happened?
詳しくは分かりませんが 賢人たちが
王の逆鱗に触れて 明朝処刑されます
I didn’t hear everything,
but the wise men angered the king.
Everyone is to be executed by dawn.
Bring Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah here.
ハナニヤ ミシャエル アザリヤを
連れてきてください 相談します
I’ll try to learn more.
Yes—Chaldean, Egyptian, Jewish
カルデア人 エジプト人
ユダヤ人 賢人たち全員だ
—all the wise men.
Arioch?
アルヨク
ベルテシャザル こんな所で何してる？
Belteshazzar, you shouldn’t be here.
なぜ王はこんな厳しい命令を
出したのですか
Why is there such a harsh order from the king?
He had a dream,
王が夢を見た
でもどんな夢だったか誰も話せない
and no one can tell him what it is.
すぐ逃げろ！夜明けまでに逃げるんだ
さもないと殺される！
Flee now!
If you escape before dawn, you might survive.
Tell me why I asked for them
集めろと言ったのに
なぜ連れてこないんだ？
and you haven’t brought them?
どうして占っても分からないんだ？
Why aren’t the gods talking to them?
I want them and all of their families brought here.
家族もろとも連れてこい
I want to look into the whites of their eyes
問いただしてやる
and ask them why.
Hang them without their skins!
皮を剝いではりつけにしろ！
Let the gods look down on their flesh,
神々に見せつけてやれ！
それからユーフラテスに投げ込むんだ！
and then throw their bodies in the Euphrates.
アシュペナズ！
Ashpenaz.
賢人のくせに分からないのか！
What good are wise men without wisdom?
何が賢人だ！
こんな所で何してる？
What are you doing here?
王にお話しさせてください
I need to speak with the king.
You need to go!
すぐ逃げるんだ！
Please, let me speak with him!
お願いです 話させてください
My lord, this is Belteshazzar.
王よ ベルテシャザルがお話ししたいと
O king,
王よ
interpretations belong to my God, Jehovah.
私の神エホバなら解き明かせます
He knows your dream and what it means.
王が見た夢と その意味を
じゃあ おまえの神の言葉を聞かせろ！
Well, where is your God? Where?
I believe that he—
エホバはきっと
I know that he will reveal it to me.
いや必ず夢を解き明かしてくださいます
どうか時間をください
Please, give me time.
We have until morning.
朝までに何とかしないと
To do what?
何を？
王が見た夢をお話しするんだ
To reveal the dream to the king.
Well, how much of the dream
で エホバはなんて？
has Jehovah revealed to you?
Well, nothing yet.
まだ何も
But Jehovah revealed
でもエホバは 夢の意味を
解き明かすと言ってくれた
that he would interpret it, right?
そういうことだよね？
Not exactly.
いや・・・
Daniel,
ダニエル じゃあどうするつもりなの？
how do you know this is even going to happen?
うーん 分からない
Well, I can’t be sure.
分からないじゃ困るよ！
You’d better be sure!
これにはエホバの名誉が懸かっている
His name is at stake.
If he reveals the dream,
もし明らかにしてくだされば
本当の神だって分かる
it proves that he’s the true God!
駄目だったら？
If?
どうしたらいい？
What can we do to help?
祈ってほしい エホバが憐れみを
掛けてくださるようにと
Pray.
Pray that Jehovah have mercy on us.
O Jehovah,
エホバ
surely you didn’t bring us here just to die.
ここに来たのは
死ぬためではないはずです
この国の人たちはどう思うでしょうか
What will people say?
We told them that you
あなたが天の神で 秘密を明らかにする
本当の神だと言ってしまいました
are the God of the heavens,
the only God who can reveal secrets.
Please,
どうか 力をお示しください
vindicate yourself.
Jerah!
エラハ！
I have found a man from the exiles of Judah
ユダで捕らえた人の中で王の夢を
解き明かせる者を見つけました
who can make known the interpretation to the king.
誰かは分かっている
I know who he is.
おまえは本当に私が見た夢の
内容を話し 解き明かせるのか
Can you really make known to me
the dream that I saw
and its interpretation?
There is a God in the heavens
秘密を明らかにされる神が
天におられます
who is a Revealer of secrets,
and he has made known to King Nebuchadnezzar
その方が 最後の日々に起きる事柄を
what is to happen in the final part of the days.
ネブカドネザル王に知らせたのです
これが あなたが見た夢です
This is your dream:
王は巨大な像をご覧になりました
You saw an immense image.
That image was standing in front of you.
その像があなたの前に立っていました
You yourself are the head of gold.
あなたこそが金の頭です
あなたの後に 劣った別の王国
But after you another kingdom will rise,
inferior to you.
銀のものが生じます
Then another kingdom,
次いで別の王国
a third one, of copper,
3番目の銅のものが生じ
全世界を支配します
that will rule over the whole earth.
As for the fourth kingdom,
4番目の王国は
鉄のように強いものとなります
it will be strong like iron.
The kingdom will be divided.
この王国は分裂することになります
And as the toes of the feet
足の指には鉄の部分と
粘土の部分があるので
were partly of iron and partly of clay,
この王国には強い部分と
もろい部分があることになります
so the kingdom will be partly strong
and partly fragile.
この王たちの時代に 天の神は決して
滅ぼされることのない王国を建てます
In the days of those kings,
the God of heaven
will set up a kingdom
that will never be destroyed.
And this kingdom
その王国はほかの
どんな民にも渡されません
will not be passed on to any other people.
It will crush and put an end
これらの王国を全て打ち砕いて終わらせ
to all these kingdoms.
And it alone will stand forever.
その王国だけが永遠に存続します
The dream is true,
この夢は真実であり
and its interpretation is trustworthy.
解き明かしも確かです
Quick!
早く！上等の服を持ってこい！
Bring a fine robe
and a necklace of gold.
金の首飾りも
香をたけ
Burn incense before him.
あなた方の神はまさしく 神の中の神
Truly your God is a God of gods
王たちの主 秘密を明らかにされる方だ
and a Lord of kings
and a Revealer of secrets.
May your God be honored
あなた方の神を私はたたえる
by the honor I give you.
You are now ruler over all the province of Babylon.
あなたにバビロン州全体を
治めてもらおう
O king, these servants
王よ この者たちも
天の神エホバを崇拝しています
also worship the God in the heavens.
May they too be appointed to administer the province?
彼らにも務めをお与えいただけますか
Make the necessary arrangements.
そうしてやれ
君たちはずば抜けている
You have proven far superior
この賢人たちがかすんで見える
than these so-called wise men.
I now appoint you their chief prefect.
これからはおまえが賢人たちを仕切れ
Did you hear Nebuchadnezzar?
王の言葉 聞いた？
When he said, “Your God is a God of gods
「あなた方の神はまさしく
神の中の神 王たちの主」
and a Lord of kings.”
君の祈りが聞かれたね
Jehovah answered your prayer.
いや 僕たちみんなの祈りだ
Jehovah answered our prayers.
これからどうなるんだろう？
What’s going to happen next?
エルサレムに帰れるのかな？
Can we go back to Jerusalem?
I don’t know what happens next,
分からない
でもエホバから離れないなら・・・
but as long as we stay close to Jehovah . . .
He will always be with us
信仰を持ち続けるなら
エホバは共にいてくださる
as long as we have faith in him.
いくら星を読んでも この国が
砕かれるなんてあり得ません
There’s nothing in the stars
about kingdoms crushing kingdoms.
当たり前だ！
Of course not.
見事なトリックだ
It’s a trick!
でも夢はどうやって？
But how did he know the dream?
アマルウトゥ！
Amar-Utu!
神々からのお告げはあったか？
Amar-Utu, what message from the gods?
羊の肝臓で占いました
未来は安泰です
I have examined a sheep’s liver.
Your future is bright.
偉大な星シャバトゥによれば
あなたは栄え続けます
The stars of Shabatu, the giant,
speak only of your grandeur.
私は黄金の頭だ！エホバがそう言った
And I’m the head of gold.
Jehovah said so.
王の夢は確かにめでたい夢です
でも ベルテシャザルはユダヤ人です
Your dream revealed many good things.
But this Belteshazzar, he’s a Jew—
He’s a clever Jew, to be sure,
確かに賢い それは認めましょう
but he couldn’t interpret dreams
しかし 夢を解き明かすすべは
バビロンで学んだのではないでしょうか
before he came to Babylon.
He first had to be educated here
and given a Babylonian name,
この国で教育を受け
バビロニアの名をもらいました
a name that honors our great god Bel.
偉大な神ベルにちなんだ名前です
ベルがこの若者を通して
メッセージを伝えたのです
Bel used this young captive
to reveal great things to you—
Bel,
ベルです
not Jehovah, who you defeated in Jerusalem.
エホバではありません
木は私の敵ということか
So the tree is my enemies.
Who is it after the seven times pass over?
では 7つの時が
過ぎた後もそうなのか？
それはあなたです 王よ
Then it is you again, O great king.
You are fools.
さっぱり意味が分からん！
At last—
待ってたぞ ベルテシャザル
Belteshazzar, chief of the magic-practicing priests,
おまえは魔術師の長だ
all of the other wise men are unable
ほかの魔術師は誰も
意味を説明できなかった
to make the interpretation known to me.
おまえならできるだろう
But you are able to do so.
私が見た夢の意味を説明してほしい
Explain to me the visions I’ve seen in my dreams.
どんな夢ですか
What did you dream?
大地の真ん中に高い木が
I saw a tree in the midst of the earth,
非常に高い木が立っていた
and its height, it was enormous
—it was enormous.
その木は成長して強くなり
And the tree grew and became strong,
頂が天に達して 天に達して
強くなり 高くなった
and its top—
And its top reached the heavens,
reached the heavens,
and the tree grew and became strong.
聖なる者が この木を
切り倒しなさい！⋯⋯
. . . holy one . . .
Chop down the tree!
And I saw a watcher . . .
見張りの者が この木を
切り倒しなさい！⋯⋯
Chop down the tree!
. . . with a banding of iron
鉄と銅のたがだ
and of copper.
この木はいったい何なんだ？
So who’s the tree?
O my lord,
王よ
may the dream apply to those hating you
この夢があなたを
憎む者たちに当てはまり
あなたの敵に当てはまるとよいのですが
and its interpretation to your enemies.
あなたがご覧になった木
The tree that you saw
すなわち 成長して大きく強くなり
that grew great and became strong,
whose top reached the heavens
頂が天に達して地の果てからも見え
and was visible to all the earth,
葉が美しく茂り 豊かに実がなって
which had beautiful foliage, abundant fruit,
and food for all,
全てのものを養うことができ
beneath which the beasts of the field would dwell
木陰に野獣が集まり
and on whose branches
枝に鳥がすみ着いた木
the birds of the heavens would reside,
it is you, O king.
それは王ご自身です
And the king saw a watcher, a holy one,
そして 見張りの者 聖なる者が
天から下ってきてこう言いました
coming down from the heavens who was saying:
「この木を切り倒して損ないなさい⋯⋯
“Chop down the tree and destroy it,
しかし 切り株と根は地面に残し
“but leave the stump with its roots in the ground
“with a banding of iron and of copper.
鉄と銅のたがをはめて放置しなさい
“And let the dew of the heavens make it wet,
天からの露にぬれるままにし
“and let its portion be
野獣と共に生かしておきなさい
“with the beasts of the field
until seven times pass over it.”
7つの時が過ぎるまで」
This is the interpretation, O king;
王よ これが解き明かしです
it is the decree of the Most High.
これは至高者の布告です
You will be driven away from among men,
あなたは人々の中から追いやられ
野獣とすみかを共にし
and your dwelling will be with the beasts of the field,
雄牛のように草を食べることになります
and you will be given vegetation to eat
just like bulls,
and you will become wet
天からの露にぬれるままになり
with the dew of the heavens,
こうして7つの時が過ぎます
and seven times will pass over you
until you know
そしてあなたは 至高者が
人間の王国の統治者であり
that the Most High is Ruler
in the kingdom of mankind
ご自分の望む者にそれを
与えるということを知るのです
and that he grants it to whomever he wants.
But because they said to leave
切り株と根は残されたので
王国は再びあなたのものになります
the stump of the tree with its roots,
your kingdom will be yours again
天が治めているということを
あなたが知った後にです
after you come to know
that the heavens are ruling.
Turn away from your sins
正しいことを行って罪から離れ
by doing what is right
and from your iniquity
貧しい人たちに憐れみを示してください
by showing mercy to the poor.
It may be that your prosperity will be extended.
そうすれば 繁栄が続くかもしれません
ベルテシャザルはいつ
そうなるかを知ってるのか？
Does Belteshazzar know when this will happen?
No.
いえ 分からないようです
しかも賢人たちは
あの解釈は怪しいと言っています
But your wise men
doubt that his interpretation can be trusted.
考えてもみてください
Look at the facts:
Egypt’s gods told the Egyptians
エジプトの神々も
エジプトがバビロンに勝つ
と言っていませんでしたか
that they would defeat us.
でも 勝ったのはあなたです
Yet, you destroyed them.
So why should the God of the Jews
ユダヤ人の神もその程度
恐れるに足りません
be given any more credit?
Look at what you’ve done.
目を覚ましてください
The gods are with you.
神々が味方です
あなたがバビロンを
世界最強の帝国にしたのです
You have made Babylon
the greatest kingdom on earth.
Belteshazzar wants you to grovel like a slave
ベルテシャザルはあなたを
手玉に取ろうとしています
王であるあなたを
—you.
あんな若造に振り回されないでください
A strong king means a strong kingdom.
エンリルの星についての講義を続けよう
Let us continue with our discussion
of the stars of Enlil.
分かってるだろうが
ルガルがウルグラ座で一番明るい星だ
Now, the Lugal star is the brightest star
in the Urgula constellation.
星はうそをつかない
The stars are reliable,
負けた国の神々とは違う
unlike the gods of defeated nations.
エルサレムにお帰りになりますか
Go back to Jerusalem.
Oh, you could
あっ 失礼 エルサレムは
まだ廃虚でしたね
if there was anything left of it.
エホバからのお告げはありましたか
Has Jehovah revealed anything new?
あれからもう10カ月です
It’s been ten months
誰かが言ってましたね
王の気が狂うって
and still no sign of this supposed insanity.
神がそう言ったんです
I trust my God.
私たちも星で神のお告げを確かめている
Yes, as we do when we read the stars.
でも違う結果が出ているんです
But we still shape the message.
このままでは
ただでは済まないでしょうね
You will be held responsible for the words,
and when a wise man speaks lies, well . . .
賢人がでたらめを言ったとなると
どうなると思いますか？
エホバが明らかにしたことを
話しただけです
I spoke only what Jehovah revealed.
夢を正しく解き明かせなかった
賢人たちは処刑されかけた
Have you forgotten what happened
when some couldn’t interpret the dream image?
A death sentence followed.
あの説明は見事だった
And that was a flattering interpretation,
王が金の頭だと
that the king was a head of gold.
This time, you’ve said he’ll go mad,
このたびは 気が触れると言った
and nothing has happened.
でも何も起きていない
必ずそうなります
It will happen.
さて それはどうかな？
Maybe, maybe not.
王を侮辱したことになります
But your words are against the king.
反逆罪だ
It’s treason.
もう助けようがありませんね
And no one can protect you from that.
Ten months.
あれからもう10カ月です
Nothing has happened.
でも何も起きていない
But your words are against the king.
王を侮辱したことになります
Still no sign of this supposed insanity.
誰かが言ってましたね
王の気が狂うって
It’s treason.
反逆罪だ
And no one can protect you from that.
もう助けようがありませんね
So you can always have Jehovah’s words with you.
エホバの言葉を忘れちゃいけないよ
「エホバ あなたの道を
教えてください」
“Instruct me in your way, O Jehovah.”
“Do not hand me over to my adversaries,
「敵対者の手に私を渡さないでください
“for false witnesses have risen up against me,
偽りを語る証人が立ち上がり
“and they threaten me with violence.
私を激しく脅してきます
“Where would I be if I did not have faith
もし私に信仰がなかったなら
どうなっていただろう
エホバの善い行いを見ることを
信じていないなら」
“that I would see Jehovah’s goodness
in the land of the living?”
どうか 私たちを
10日の間試してください
Please, test your servants for ten days.
Somehow, you look healthier than the others.
でも みんな元気そうだ
これからも 希望する
食べ物を出してあげなさい
Continue giving them the diet they’ve requested.
おまえたちの神のことはよく知らないが
I do not know your God,
but you’ve proven
おまえたちは国中の
どの魔術師よりも10倍優れている
to be ten times better than any priest
or conjurer I’ve met.
He had a dream,
王が夢を見た
でもどんな夢だったか誰も話せない
and no one can tell him what it is.
Jehovah answered your prayer.
君の祈りが聞かれたね
“Hope in Jehovah;
「希望を抱いてエホバを待て
“be courageous and strong of heart.
勇気を出し 心を強くせよ
Yes, hope in Jehovah.”
そうだ 希望を抱いてエホバを待て」
ベルに犠牲を捧げるんだ
Prepare a sacrifice to Bel.
To the gods.
乾杯
美しい！世界一の都市だ
This city is the jewel of the world.
Look at the Ishtar Gate, the gardens,
イシュタル門 空中庭園
the ziggurat so high
そびえ立つジッグラト
天にも達する勢いだ
it reaches the gods themselves.
その通りでございます
No one would question that.
思えば1年前
It’s odd that only twelve months ago
王の気が触れるなどと失礼なことを
言った家臣がおりましたが・・・
one of your servants
dared to suggest that you’d go insane.
私はこの大いなるバビロンを
王家のために
Is this not Babylon the Great
また私の輝かしい威光を示すために
that I myself have built for the royal house
with my own strength and might
自分の偉大な力で築いたのだ
and for the glory of my majesty?
“To you it is being said,
「ネブカドネザル王 あなたに告げます
“O King Nebuchadnezzar,
“‘The kingdom has gone away from you,
“‘and from mankind you are being driven away.
『王国はあなたから取り去られました
“‘With the beasts of the field your dwelling will be,
あなたは人々の中から追いやられ
“‘and you will be given vegetation
野獣とすみかを共にし
“‘to eat just like bulls,
雄牛のように草を食べることになり
“‘and seven times will pass over you,
こうして7つの時が過ぎます
“‘until you know that the Most High
そしてあなたは 至高者が
人間の王国の統治者であり
“‘is Ruler in the kingdom
“‘of mankind and that he grants it
ご自分の望む者にそれを与える
ということを知るのです』」
to whomever he wants.’”
No! Stop! Stop! Stop!
うわあ
父上！
何だ！
Father!
父上！
うわあ
Father!
父上！
あなたと賢人たちは 自分たちのことは
棚に上げてダニエルを訴えるつもりか
When you and your wise men
have failed consistently,
how can you claim Daniel to be a fraud?
これはトリックです
父君に対する ダニエルの謀反です
This was a trick.
Daniel conspired against your father.
A trick.
ほう じゃあ ダニエルは
どんな方法を使ったんだ？
Then how did he make it happen?
いずれにしても ダニエルが
言ったことは全部その通りになった
Everything he has said has come true,
which is quite different from our history with you.
My father trusted you,
あなたたちとは大違いだ
and I trusted you, and you were all wrong.
父上も私もあなたたちを信じていたが
それは間違いだった
Either you failed or Marduk did.
Either way, . . .
あなたたちのせいか
マルドゥクのせいかは分からないが
とにかく・・・
Tell me:
教えてほしい
Who is this God in the heavens, Jehovah?
天の神エホバとは
一体どんな神なんだ？